good evening everyone i now call to order this april 8th 2025 meeting of lancaster city council a few reminders at the top of the meeting for everyone with us tonight please take a moment to silence your devices phones if you haven't done so already this meeting and its participants are being recorded and live streamed anyone addressing council during public comment periods should do so at the microphone here in front of us to be heard both in the room and on the live stream please begin all comments with your name and block of residence for our meeting record public comment is limited to three minutes per speaker and i will use the light that's here in front of me to keep time it will turn green when a speaker begins it will flash yellow when there is one minute remaining and will flash red when time has been expended and i want to thank all of you in advance for ensuring that everyone has equal time this evening for all of those who are willing and able please rise for the pledge of allegiance mr harris would you please call the the roll of members yes madam president mr. man here mr. Roya here mr. Cleese
here miss Craig here miss Diaz mr. Hirsch here in prison
Baker here councillor Diaz is excused this evening next item is the approval of the minutes of the March 25th 2025 meeting motion to approve second we have a motion and a second for our meeting minutes councillors any comments on
those minutes very none mr. Harris mr. man I mr. Roy oh hi mr. Glees I miss Craig all right mr. Hirsch hi president Baker I write our next item on the
agenda this evening proclamations honors awards and resolutions of recognition we have won this evening resolution number 23 2025 mr. Harris if you would a
resolution of the Council of the City of Lancaster designating April 2025 as sexual assault awareness month in the city of lancaster pennsylvania motion to approve second
thank you we have a motion and a second counselors thank you very much for allowing me to introduce this resolution again this year april is sexual assault awareness month and it brings awareness that sexual violence continues to be widespread and affect all members of our community during this month resolution i'd like to proudly affirm that the lancaster ywca is still lancaster county's designated rape crisis center and applaud the work that they do in our community for sexual assault prevention and counseling all at no cost they are hosting numerous events this month to help raise awareness support survivors and promote prevention efforts and I'd like to invite the team from the YWCA to the podium this evening to say a few words good evening and thank you for being here good
evening thank you my name is Theo work at the YWCA Lancaster sexual assault prevention counseling center this is my colleague Maddie Ressler who also works at the Sexual Assault Prevention Counseling Center. I just wanted to take a few moments to talk about what we offer as services for both the council and for the public. So like you said we offer counseling and therapy services at no cost to both victim survivors of sexual violence as well as their significant others which could be family members, partners friends, neighbors, anyone who else who is impacted by that violence as well. we have a 24 7 sexual assault hotline that you can call in any time of the day we're on call for you you can call in if you need resources someone to talk to or want to get set up for our services and that number is 7 1 7 3 9 2 7 2 7 3 and again that's 24 7 we're always here for you we have medical accompaniment we accompany victim survivors of sexual violence to the hospitals again at no costs to help them through the process and offer support similarly similar well that's a hard word similarly nope as well as legal accompaniment we do offer legal accompaniment as well and that's to court proceedings all throughout the way even police interviews for victim survivors of sexual violence again that's at no cost we want to be there with all of the systems that victim survivors of sexual violence are interacting with so we try to be at each moment we can we also do a lot of prevention education for the community we go to schools workplaces churches community organizations anywhere really that we can talk about prevention around sexual violence and around consent boundaries handling difficult feelings healthy relationships and that's something if you're interested in as for your organization you can always go on website and the programs that we offer are on there as well um am i missing anything buddy um
i would just add that we also have support groups as part of our set of services the first monday of each month so actually it was just last night we have an adult survivor gathering that happens from six to seven pm at the lime street location of ywca lancaster so it's right around the corner and all of those services that we've listed are also available in any language we have interpretation services through PCAR which is the Pennsylvania Coalition to Advance Respect so we're able to call them or even bring them in in person again at no cost to offer those services to anyone in any language so we're trying to take down as many barriers as possible there
it's everything thank you thank you so much for being here this evening counselors are there any council comments on this resolution of recognition comments from the public hearing none mr. Harris mr. man aye mr.
Roya aye mr. Glees aye miss Craig all right mr. Hirsch aye the president
Baker aye thank you and counselors we will I have a presentation copy to present to our YWCA staff this evening and we can adjourn to this side of the room to take a brief photo if everyone would bear with us while we do that and do you have someone to take the photo fabulous okay we will be right back
thank you our next item on the agenda this evening is our first public comment
period this is reserved for residents who contacted the city clerk prior to the meeting to request the opportunity to address council again the cutoff is two o'clock today for these comments so these are the folks that come or excuse me these are the folks that requested to speak before two o'clock today duration of comments is limited to three minutes per speaker and again please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record mr. Harris our first
speaker this evening yes madam president our first speaker is Russell Durfee good
evening if you see the green light you're good that might not be on do you
see the green light there now there we go so over the past few meetings we've heard feedback from the mayor regarding her views on I guess the ineffectiveness of civilian or rewards and the general challenges to reform posed by the city's agreements with the police or police unions to the extent that these views are valid they clearly represent a significant roadblock to the progress that the community is demanding so after reflecting on this I just have some questions for the council that I hope are constructive but I also will acknowledge that probably can't be answered here tonight and I appreciate the opportunity to continue the conversation outside of this in person or an email however so the first question is what I'd like to know what is the city the status of the city's collective bargaining agreement with the please and where the public can access this information I tried to find a current agreement and can only find an agreement signed by the mayor that was due to expire in December of 2022 and my understanding is that sometimes union contracts can continue past their expiration date unless they're compelled back to the renegotiation table so I was just wondering if that's the case here in general what would be the council's plans for upcoming renegotiations with the police union or the police given the feedback that the constituents you serve have given over the past month this is my question question two is there potential to include the establishment of a civilian review board in any and i'll say one with actual authority because i know that's been a question in the re to include that in the renegotiations of the city and the police um i think the mayor's comments have made clear that the police will not in good faith address the community's demands if they come from a civilian review board or really any entity for that matter if they don't have the proper authority so i'm questioning if that authority exists at all in the city right now frankly and i feel like a lot of us are maybe including the mayor so a civilian review board with real authority would require adequate funding which could be tied to the police budget to discourage attempts to undercut that funding it would have independent investigative power and access to police records including body camera footage i'll say too having looked into this that i understand that the president that's been set in states like Connecticut and New Jersey where frankly the biggest power for a civilian review board is subpoena power and that has largely come from state legislatures not municipal like this but I think the important fact to recognize is that subpoena power isn't given unless there's a civilian review board to give it to we are trying to lay the groundwork for that
I appreciate your comments but we've hit three minutes if I may endeavor to answer your first question and then I do have your okay yeah I just
think that if the alternative is nothing nothing's not enough this is part of the point and we could fund this possibly which was going to be my third question with the emergency relief funds I'd love to learn more about how we can use those funds even if that's to replace the police department if we do go to the negotiating table and they don't like the deal you know like I'd like to know
what those funds are for as well thank you but to your question about the current collective bargaining agreement it has been negotiated since then I don't know exactly where to find it but I can help with that and the current one is in effect through um is it 2026 or 2020 the end of 2025. 12 31 2026 12 31 2026. i knew it and then i wanted to verify that i was back so thank you
uh mr harris our next public commenter for this period yes good evening thanks for having me um and thanks for all that you do i know that it takes out a lot of time of your personal lives i really appreciate it I'm here to talk a little bit about the groups of kids that I've witnessed and seen and I hate that that's kids because oh my name Karen Schlaer how about we start there Boys and Girls Clubs of Lancaster my properties are West Lemon Street Water Street and Duke Street so back to talking about the groups of folks that I've seen traveling on bikes that have been unsafe and this has been over the course of the last two to three years that we've witnessed this I really feel like this is a safety issue it's a community problem that we have to address and I would like to be solution driven I don't think kids need to be taught to not ride in and out of traffic and down the middle of the road I think those are basic skills that kids learn we all learn to not ride our bikes that way I've experienced groups of keep referring to them as kids but I've recently learned that they are young adults some of them and that's been difficult for us to handle because we only handle and deal with kids we have had on multiple occasions reached out to some of those adults to have meetings to have conversations to find a healthy way to have fun on bikes and not have a thrill of danger on bikes. For those that don't know, my office is on Vine and Water Street. My window looks over the corner of Vine and Water Street. The things that I witness when I'm taking a little break from emails and look out my window and see the hordes of kids, young adults popping wheelies and burning through that stop sign terrifies me actively scares me and I don't want that on our conscience what the club has done as I said reach out to some of the young adults trying to come up with more conversations we've had one already we've also applied for a grant for bike racks so that kids can safely park their bikes at Boys and Girls Clubs it's the only properties I can control so our three locations will have brand new bike racks hopefully by the spring because I do think that that's some of the fear that the kids have with leaving their bikes out some of the bikes are quite expensive also we're starting a bike riding group that will be led with staff it will start over in the southeast neighborhood and be led by staff and will teach positive etiquette for kids to enjoy safe bike riding I see the
light thank you thank you thank you
good evening everyone good evening council good evening fellow community members my name is Ricardo Calderon I live in the Willow Street area today I'm representing the mix and would like to speak on our relationship with the police department and I have a few words I would share afterwards but wanting to share that we obviously know that the relationship between the police department and community while we're one is very complex and that's been around for as long as we can remember. Narrative is really important though and adding to that narrative really want to share the powerful relationship we have whether that's through the PAL program, whether that's through our work with the police department, through our call to action committee, which we see one of our partners here, and coming together to really try to address the violence in our city, whether that's through National Night Out, Art in the Park. If you've ever seen a bunch of kiddos having a really good time on the corner of Orange and Duke, Orange and Prince Street, that was us having a really good time. For those of you who are not aware who the mix is or what we do, we're a non-profit organization that really specializes around after-school programming and out-of-school time initiatives trying to foster really powerful educational environments for our young people and families. And while I'm not here to specifically talk about a specific issue, I do know that humanizing our police officers and our young people and communities is really important. We will always have young people riding bikes and wanting to do things. That's never going to change. My little girl is learning how to ride a bike right now and I'd stop her from going into the street yesterday and she's four years old um what I would love to see as a community is how we continue to humanize these important roles in our community and I think that starts with building relationships um and the reason I wanted to come and speak on behalf of the mix is because we see that within our doors when the police officers come into our building we try very hard to establish a relationship not seeing the officer in uniform but the human behind the badge um to be able to understand what they're going through to be able to understand what young people are going through so no doubt we have many many issues that we have to take on I just want to encourage us whether it's through the policies that we're looking to do whether it's great initiatives such as the bike ride how do we continue to find humanity and what we do and building those relationships because independent of what we try to do young people will be young people and I think as adults it's our job to make sure that we're carefully building those relationships so there's a connection so there's an understanding so when there are altercations humans are engaging with each other not opposition I think that's very very important in our community especially given the landscape of today's world where everything is very extreme everything is on either side narratives are running how we feel about people how we choose to act so I really really hope that we can come together and figure out ways not just from a storytelling perspective but also a relationship building perspective how we're doing that for our community and and for our students in particular our young folks so really appreciate the time today a lot of respect for what we're all doing here as we all play a role in this and again i just want to re-emphasize um humanizing each other we need to go back to humanizing who we are and finding our human in this space appreciate you all thank you mr calderon mr harris our next speaker next is
will keifer mr keifer good evening good evening city council and mayor sirachi thanks for having having me in tonight, I will add to this discussion. I just want to paint a picture of some really important work being done collaboratively between the organization that I lead, which is Benchmark Program. We're at the intersection of Prince and Vine, very close to the Boys and Girls Club. So the work between Benchmark Program and our local police force. In May or March of last year, we were awarded this grant from the Pennsylvania Commission on Crime and Delinquency called a VIP grant, Violence Intervention and Prevention. a three-year grant and it's beginning to target or to support kids who have been involved with some kind of firearm related crime but aren't being charged so at our organization we have pathways to support kids who have gotten formally charged they're incarcerated at the Youth Intervention Center we have programs for them but what we haven't been able to serve and what we can't do without our police department is I can't connect with the kids who are at that scene who are detained and then who are released back home the police are the only ones at that incident who know those kids and through this grant from the Pennsylvania Crime Commission on Crime and Delinquency we now have a pathway for police to get parent permission to release information about those children to benchmark so that we can provide a one-on-one mentor for them now we go to the house connect with parents connect with the kid this is all voluntary no one who is detained by the police and sent home has to come to benchmark but finally through this proactive approach with police we have a chance to connect with those kids and I'm not sure they'd otherwise just walk into benchmark program for services so I'm grateful to the police department for doing that work I view that as upstream work connecting with kids before they get a formal charge and statistically the kids who are at one of those crime scenes and sent back home without any formal charges are actually most likely to perpetuate violence so we now have this chance to connect with them and serve them and support them when we otherwise wouldn't and I couldn't do that work without police and I don't think many people know that we're doing that work because it's quiet and it's small and it's not fixing all the problems but I think it's a start and I have to be clear that we could not do that without them and I'm grateful to them and I want to see that work
continue. And that's all. Thank you very much. Mr. Harris, our next speaker this evening. Next speaker is Janet Simms. Is Ms. Simms here? No? Okay. I'll call her at the conclusion and the second period just in case that she comes in. After Ms. Simms, Mr. Harris? It is Mimi Shapiro. Good evening. Good evening and thank you for letting me
me speak. I live at 239 North Concord Street in Lancaster and I think everybody up there knows me. I am only speaking as a person and from my personal perspective. I am here tonight because I believe that our Lancaster City Police are good human beings and excellent policemen. They protect our community but more important they care about public safety this is a public safety problem kids need to learn real-life lessons to have respect for rules and laws for everybody's safety I am an educator having worked with students of all ages I know that sometimes kids do not think of the consequences but imagine if they hit someone or if a driver hit one of them I I have witnessed kids driving their bikes in traffic recklessly, doing wheelies with only one tire on the ground, moving in and out on Duke Street, on Mulberry at King, again at Charlotte and West Chestnut. These kids are just fooling around. It's frightening to me as a pedestrian, since I have been hit by a car and had two broken legs. Healing takes a long, long time with lots and lots of physical therapy besides learning to walk again. Public safety, to quote Mayor Ernie Triano of Wildwood, New Jersey, listen, this isn't a suggestion, it's the law. We are not playing games. When it comes to the safety of others, you break the rules, you pay the consequences. There are actually consequences for your actions. so i know that the police do an amazing job trying to get everybody and figure it all out but they are not our enemies they are here for us so thank you very much for letting me speak
thank you mr mr harris our next speaker next speaker
good evening council arthur morris 400 block of west chestnut street My comments relate, as other comments have here this evening, to the police arrests of teenagers who were riding bikes on North Queen Street last month. I've previously witnessed this behavior by youth on bikes. They were cutting across traffic, doing wheelies, and generally showing off their skills. I'm sure they were having fun, but this was not the place for it. The behavior was reckless and a public safety threat to them, pedestrians, and drivers. I want to thank our police and the mayor for taking this action. Such reckless behavior must not be tolerated. Two other comments. I believe the police used reasonable methods to restrain these youth, which would not have been easy to do. These kids are in great shape and they're quick. And I don't like the fact that the police have to put themselves in a position where they can get hurt as well. I do not believe they used excessive force. I appreciate those that spoke about connecting our youth with police and others to improve their lives. However, in the meantime, I urge parents and other adults who are associated with youth involved to take them to the police station. have them apologize, and then discuss what public service they can perform to help mitigate the consequences they face. This can be a learning experience when managed correctly. Thank you very much for your time.
Thank you, Mayor Morris. Our next speaker, Mr. Harris, is Jessica Lopez. Good evening.
Good evening. I'm going to present you. Jessica Lopez, Lancaster City. Hope everybody's having a good evening. let me start by saying that this narrative that it's okay to be on black and brown children for not having bike lights and popping willies in the street needs to stop the conversations that were had here like I get the comments I get the concerns yes and I love the fact that we do have organizations like this for our kids but this set narrative from our community members that would never understand the issues of the black and brown community that is okay to put hands on children over riding bikes is crazy now the proposal I just handed you guys is a proposal that was given to the Baltimore Police Department in regards to use the force tactics on youth it highlights issues of certain tactics and why they should not be utilized on children. It gives solutions and I believe that this this form right here could lead you into how to really deal with the issues that are transpiring with the police department and our youth. I don't believe that we can keep ignoring the fact that our children are being traumatized. Harm is harm. It don't have to be a car that hits them it was a cop that hit them so how are they supposed to go throughout their lives trusting police officers now you don't trust crossing the street and they don't trust cops this narrative is wrong yeah I've come in here week after week and yelled and screamed and maybe you heard me maybe used it now I'm giving you solutions we are presenting you with with solution after solution and beyond just screaming and user telling us no after no after no this can't be done no these things can be done these things can be incorporated in that union contract there are things that can be done to protect the citizens not just our police officers so I really urge you to take this into consideration I really urge you to pass this on to Chief Mendez who openly admitted that there were no difference in how they treat adults than how they treat children and that is a problem he really stood here and it felt like it was okay and he was proud of the fact and the way his officers treat our kids that's not just our kids y'all have kids intertwined in this situation somewhere that you know and love this could be any one of them and yes we love the orgs that keep them out the way that still does not change how the police officers deal with our children thank
you good evening Tony Dasha 700 block of New
Holland Avenue City Council I fell off my bike and hurt my leg I've been trying to take it easy especially since this weekend I had to beat Thaddeus Stevens for living the experience get your tickets today by the the way, and sometimes I wonder if I have to be Thaddeus Stevens right now, too. On account of pain, I didn't really want to be here tonight except for one item later under ordinances for first reading that needed attending to tonight. I know I can't miss it, so since I needed to be here physically, I figured I'd offer a free show in three acts. Not living the experience, welcome to the tony show in this first act why i'm physically present at all during the pandemic council had working systems to meet and allow participation digitally i'm not saying we should go hybrid tomorrow but i don't think it would take much a few steps and planning over a couple months to get there when it comes to live streaming and access i've often thought the city of lancaster has been good enough post see-through city days but moments like this make me realize that good Good enough often just means good enough for now. And just because we're a walkable city doesn't mean someone limping like me tonight should have to come to 120 North Duke to make their public comments heard. And an obvious counterpoint, just because someone can stay home doesn't mean that they will. I believe in a city where people can be heard even when it hurts to stand. The neglect of digital access, the tools that let the meek speak and the lame stand should trouble us all because we've used these tools before. We know they work. The question is now whether we still believe everyone deserves a seat at the table, even if they can't make it to the room. Thank you.
Thank you, Mr. Adams. Mr. Harris, do we have any additional speakers in the first period?
We do not.
Thank you. Just to double-check, Janet Sims? I didn't see her come into the room. OK. We will now move into our next item the agenda which was reports requested by council we do not believe we have any of those tonight is that correct we do not thank you mr harris next item is reports of committees of council these are the meetings held on april 1st 2025. we began with the public safety committee councillor diaz is not here this evening she had one item on her agenda it was a report to council public works committee councillor hirsch thank you council president the public works committee
did meet on april 1st and discussed five items all of which appear on tonight's agenda legislative agendas resolutions resolution 27-2025 authorizes application for pen the penvest loan for the led service line replacement 28 authorizes application for penvest loan the large diameter water main replacement project resolution 29 states the city's intent to repay short-term financing that the funds applied for in resolution 28 of the water main replacement project and resolutions 30 and 31 authorized grant applications for south end park renovations and the reservoir park master plan respectively that concludes the report of the public works committee thank you councillor
hirsch economic development counselor met uh thank you president the economic development committee did not meet thank you finance committee councillor thank you president
the finance committee meeting our finance committee didn't uh during the last committee we heard from director campbell in an update on our budget for year end 2024 as well as the first two months of 2025 some of the highlights include that for year end 2024 most department expenses fell below budgeted amounts in the general fund the city ended the year with a 1.2 million dollar surplus that will be added to reserves in the enterprise funds that include water storm water trash. We were budgeted to end the year with deficits. The stormwater fund did end the year with a deficit, but that deficit was about $400,000 less than anticipated. The trash fund ended the year with a deficit of about $70,000 more than budgeted. The water fund was budgeted to end the year with a $160,000 deficit, but would end with a $700,000 surplus. The sewer fund was budgeted to end the year with a surplus of $1.1 million and instead ended the year with a $3.9 million surplus. That surplus was be used to establish a sewer emergency fund and regarding the first two months of the year it was still too soon to know any trends but at our next budget report we'll have a better sense of any trends for 2025. we also discussed administration resolution number 25 2025 and administration resolution number 26 2025 which will appear on the agenda later this evening
that concludes my report council president thank you very much councilor arroyo community planning
committee council correct we had one item on the agenda which was administration bill number three amending chapter 32 to authorize the sale of real property by real estate agents under specific conditions which will come up on the legislative agenda later a little later as an ordinance for
first reading thank you very much councillor Craig and personnel
committee counselor pleased the personal committee did not admit thank you very much we'll now move
into our legislative agenda this evening our first items are in the historic district uh mr harris if
you would yes considering the following application recommendation from the historical architectural review board for improvements to a property within the historic district one tonight rob white and cc crew white owners of 28 north long street requested placement of five windows on the building's facade and that application was recommended for approval by the historical
architectural vehicle motion to approve second we have a motion and a second uh counselor craig anything additional from community planning for this one no there is not it's pretty straightforward thank you very much counselors you've all been provided with the memo from the uh department about the um from uh the historic preservation specialist on this one are there any council
comments on the motion to approve from the public hearing mr harris mr matt uh mr roy
next items are ordinances for first reading this evening we have one as council craig mentioned bill number three twenty twenty five mr harris a ordinance of the lancaster city council
amending chapter 32 real property 232 3 real property sale of by adding a subpart b to allow for the sale of property by the use of realtors under specific conditions providing for the repeal of inconsistent ordinances providing for the separability ordinance and providing that the ordinance will take effect in 20 days after the date of its adoption thank you very much mr harris
again counselors this is a first read this evening i'll take any um actually i will uh counselor credit if you have any additional comments this evening i do not have any
additional comments other than the fact that this bill opens up the possibility for us to to have more options to be able to sell property when the property does come up, which is very rare for the city to have anything to sell.
Thank you very much for that. I'll also add, Councilor Craig, because there were some questions at the last meeting and I believe council has received clarification on, that any sale of property would still come before council as individual resolutions, and each time we would have the option to choose the disposition and the sale method of the property so that it just adds an extra option for council to then make that decision. Any additional council comments on the bill? Council Member.
Thank you, Council President. My only question, we did answer some of these prior, but just wanted to make sure that council would still have the authority over the process regards to the use of land and making sure the city's interests are protected and it's a real problem thank you there's Roger do you have anything to
add on that piece Thank You council president to reiterate your point this is enabling legislation that would add a potential mechanism for the sale the disposition of any properties in the process of developing a specific resolution about a specific property there would be conversation about the current zoning what the future zoning would look like related to the comprehensive plan there may be other desires that the council and the administration have for the future of that there may be we may contemplate deed restriction similar to what is used for other authorities related to the sale of properties to ensure affordability over a period of time that matches the hud requirements for affordability those things could be articulated in a resolution for the disposition of any property and they would become a part of the sales agreement and subsequently incorporated into any transaction in the future so any realtor and if we were to opt for the using a realtor or through a close bid or through a public option those things are all in play this is this is a an addition of a method right so on a
case-by-case basis we would still be able to make those decisions for each possible property that is correct thank you any additional council comments for
first reading it may be a situation in which we want to prioritize a particular use and we're looking for a sale but we're not looking to only to sell property for the maximum amount of dollars and right now the only two methods for disposing of our property basically only weight the sale price and not some of the other considerations in the same way so that is on a case-by-case
basis as well thank you any additional comments for the first reading from the
public Tony D'Astra 700 block in New Holland Avenue act 2 why this bill is bad for the public the ordinance before us administration is administration bill number three is on its surface a procedural update it allows the city to sell real estate through licensed realtors in addition to existing methods like public auction or bid and I understand the appeal it's framed as a more flexible professional and modern approach but the problem isn't the tool it's the lack of structure around how we choose to use it this bill delegates broad discretion to the mayor to initiate sales through private brokers and while council approval is required by resolution that process doesn't guarantee meaningful public involvement yes the Sunshine Act ensures the resolution will appear on a public agenda but that's a procedural minimum not an invitation to the public there's no requirement for a hearing no notice to neighbors no engagement process despite the fact the city owns over 250 acres of land within municipal boundaries about 5% of the city's footprint and there's nothing in this ordinance to ensure public land stays in public service no mention of affordable housing community ownership nonprofit partnerships just a transactional framework that could easily reward access over equity this isn't about opposing Realtors it's about opposing opacity and that's where the Charter comes in just a few months ago the people of Lancaster adopted a home rule Charter that began with a simple powerful promise we the people of city of Lancaster Pennsylvania aspire to establish the foundation of an accessible, ethical, and transparent government. This ordinance may be lawful under that charter, but it isn't faithful to its spirit. Home rule wasn't meant to free us from the constraints of state law just so we could turn inward and cut corners. It was meant to give us the tools to govern more thoughtfully, more transparently, and more in step with the people we serve. Because public land isn't just property, it's potential. And if we treat this like a line item instead of a shared resource we risk losing more than square footage we lose the opportunity to do better together as a public thank you
Darlene Byrd I'm not gonna speak long because I believe I addressed counsel at the committee meetings that you had over this and my concerns about it I will challenge counsel you know we're getting ready to have change of the guards we're talking about making and changing something basically over station six something that would affect the whole city and the real reason is because we don't know what to do with station six at the meeting we discussed about nonprofits I want to know if council has did any type of research to reach out to possibilities we talked about not having enough space for a homeless shelter we a station six that's sitting there and we're saying we don't have space for that so i want to know if there's any other thought behind getting rid of station six other than trying to change this administration resolution to not a resolution ordinance which makes it law and then changing this now i think if anything needs to be done it needs to wait till the administrative code is actually intact and presented to council to approve which you do have to prove and this is something that we did in the home road charter even as addressing the police we do have the ethics code that can address some of the issues that people are speaking about so it's all about counseling their due diligence and if you're going to make the right choices and do the right things. Thank you.
Suzy Gomez, 100 Block and North Roseboro. Just quickly, they would be an extra part of an expense on a subject line. And as I mentioned before, it hurts to go the extra mile to include exactly what Darlene just mentioned. I don't have to repeat it. i don't have to get into it i think she spoke clearly i think she spoke in english especially to the mayor there's a lot of decisions that you can make for the people for the citizens that you sworn off to defend to serve very questionable thank you miss gomez additional comments from
the public for our first reading good evening hello city council uh my name is richard boas
live in the 400 block of West Marion Street and I'm here as a resident happen to be a realtor and was not aware of this ordinance but I just wanted to present to you guys I'd recommend getting some input from Lancaster County Association of Realtors this ordinance may or may not make sense but I would use them as a resource and gain their input before you make a decision that's
thank you hi Brian Nelson I live off of up in a circle right off of Columbia Avenue and Lancaster has a homelessness problem and we've banned encampments and we've pushed them out and we were here talking about property that we could be using to benefit those individuals just so that way the city can turn a quick profit I think that it's these are options for us I think that opening this up to auctions and stuff like that you're not that's not gonna make housing affordable opens it up to private equity and that's just going to make it more expensive so I think that we need to look at you know we have all this land we've been pushing homeless people out of where they are we can't house them because there's not much space and I think that the city needs to look more at options that could be used to benefit those individuals before they try to
return of profit. Additional comments tonight for our first
reading. Hi. My name is Erin Dautrich. I live on the 300 block of New Dorch Street. I just agree with everything everyone had to say here. We as a city, we have it's obvious we have an affordable housing issue. The apartments that just opened on College Avenue, their waiting list was open for like not even a whole day. And now the waiting list is three to years long that's insane like I know personally at least five people that are looking for housing and you can't find apartments under $1,000 a month in this city that's not affordable to average people and you're talking about selling properties for profit of the city like we need properties that normal people like me and everyone I know can afford to rent the high rent prices are making it impossible to have a path to homeownership thank you thank you just to reiterate my question
earlier i mean this would give council control over what the use of the land would be on a
case-by-case basis just like it is today is that correct yes and i'll also just reiterate that
council can set parameters for the use and um uh there is not discussion i mean i know that we're talking we're complaining two things because this is related to station six because it is a piece of property that we've been trying to sell i'll just reiterate for council's uh awareness that all of the non-profit housing developers were approached about bidding on this property uh we would like to see nothing less than it become housing it is part of an r3 residential district we would appreciate if that were affordable housing and we are not necessarily looking to make a profit from the sale of this we are just trying to find the best use for the property and a buyer who will make that happen and will not let the property degrade or and not have the resources to actually make a project happen at that site and so uh again this is where we're talking about two things but we're actually not even ready to talk about station six yet because we haven't even had this conversation this is about a method of disposal of a property for a better use than uh sitting vacant right now and the council will determine the compensation
pay to the realtor um but who determines who the realtor is so that's a professional service and
that is uh typically under the purview of the administration to select uh a a party in which to sell the property the terms and conditions of that can be stipulated by council if there are concerns about it being more than what the typical compensation would be for a realtor but That is a professional service, and that is typically done by administration. But the process of what the future of the property is and so on is a conversation that will need to be had, and it would probably fall under Councilor Craig's committee should we get to that point. If we don't, we're going to put it out to private bid again. um and and i'll just remind you that again we had one bid uh that was not for housing
thank you any additional comments for the first read i'll just remind folks that uh this will come up for uh possibly a vote at our next council meeting thank you and hearing none we will move to our next item on the agenda which are resolutions this evening we do have several of those our first is resolution number 18 2025 mr harris a resolution to council the city of lancaster
authorizing the disposal of certain obsolete records and conformity with the retention and disposition schedule for records of pennsylvania municipalities
we have a motion and a second counselor he'll take this in councillor diaz's absence. This is a procedural resolution required under the record retention law. We were required and allowed to destroy paper copies of certain records. This resolution I learned refers to approximately seven paper boxes of records and I do want to confirm as we've learned since our last V-Day that all records remain and are required to remain electronically stored. So nothing is being destroyed or erased this is simply the physical paper files which are no longer required and in some cases required to be destroyed in this certain time period any additional
council comments on the resolution council president counselor thank you just uh reiterate that these uh files are still stored digitally uh and can still be requested through the right
to no act yes the public would like to that is correct additional comments from the public
jessica lopez link sdpa um thank you for clarifying that um may i suggest next time that we have something like this we know these things in advance so when these questions come up you're not getting the response that you're getting from the community if you would have have known in advance that they're digitally stored y'all could have been said that and that's just that's little things that make us feel like yous aren't doing your part in that sense because that would have been an easy response to everything we said last time would have saved yous guys a lot of time and us a lot of frustration trying to figure out what you wanted to throw away so I mean I definitely appreciate the clarification and that we are going to have them digitally stored somewhere so thank you thank you additional comments
on the resolution good evening good evening Diane Desmond I live near the state police off 30 I do also appreciate the clarification that they will be stored digitally that was also a deep concern of mine in terms of accountability and transparency in order to mend relationships and broken trust between the police and the community so I do thank you for that clarification I did have an additional question how will obsolete be defined in these cases is it just the seven year time are there other considerations for that word. I would just like to know clearly how obsolete is going to be defined, how that will be determined. Thank you.
Thank you. I can somewhat address that, although it lies a little bit out of my technical expertise, but the resolution specifically references record retention and disposition schedules um and it is um that is set by um pardon i'm just going through and reading here records of pennsylvania municipalities promulgated that's a fun word by the municipal records manual issued for the local government records committee by the pennsylvania historic museum commission bureau that's a lot of words to say that it's set at the state level so we're meeting all the requirements for record retention and uh based on the disposition of these items uh it sounds like every type of item may have a different record retention um if you've ever done an audit you know that different things have different retention schedules this sounds similar mary sirachi am i misstating anything that was very great i've done audits before um so thank you for that any additional uh council excuse me public comments on the resolution hearing none
mr harris mr matt aye mr roy aye mr hilliard aye mr craig all right mr harris aye president
aye our next item resolution number 24 2025 mr harris a resolution of the council of the city
of leicester approving the raising of the port oregon flag to to acknowledge the start of Puerto Rican Heritage Month as brought forth by Lancaster City Council we have a
motion and a second this resolution allows us allows the approval of the flying of the Puerto Rican flag on the date of the date November 18th 2025 the backup date for weather of November 19th 2025 and this request is put in by Councilor Arroyo. Councilor Arroyo, do you have anything else to add? Nothing to add,
Councilor President. Thank you very much.
Any additional council comments on the resolution? And I'll just remind everyone that there is a procedure for requesting a flag to be flown at City Hall. Those requests must be made at least 120 days in advance, so plan ahead and we would love to celebrate you at City Hall. Any public comments on resolution number 24? Hearing none, Mr. Harris.
Mr. Mayor, ah I say resolution number 25 2025 mr. Harris a resolution of the Council of
the City of Lancaster approving an amended capital project list to be funded by the proceeds of the City of Lancaster general obligation bonds
Series of 2018. Motion to approve. Second. We have a motion and a second. Councilor Arroyo. Thank you, Council President. Resolution number 25 pertains to capital projects. As they move forward, funding adjustments are needed as expenses for some projects increase and decrease for others. These adjustments are required for approval of council. These actions are not allocating additional funds. They just move money away, excuse me, just move money between previously approved projects. This specific adjustment is for $2.3 million in the sewer fund bond.
Thank you very much. Any additional comments from Council? Comments from the public on the resolution?
Darlene Bird, Anne Street. Is this my understanding that this is bonds that we got and we didn't need them for projects that were completed, so this money is left over and now Council has the power to say where that money is spent?
so these are the 2018 general bonds yeah and some projects when they were completed may have some funds left over we are required them required to move them to other projects in the fund but they must stay for their stated use of the bond so they don't go anywhere else with the projects
that were on the list that was already on the list correct thank you any additional comments
from the public on the resolution so those um those funds are going into the sewer is that
that what you said? Sewer funds? 1.3 million? Yeah, these funds are specific to the sewer fund. So that's going to go on top of the 1.4 surplus and the 3.9 million? This is pertaining to the bond that was funding projects for the 2018 bond, which is separate than what was stated before in the budget update. Okay, thank you. Thank you.
clarification did you say that the funds are going to be used toward the sewer projects because that's what she asked and i didn't hear that that were approved in the 2018 we know and now that there are funds that are left over and you're going to put them where and what capital
project so that bond approved a series of projects within that right and which where are you going to
apply that 2 million point what was it 2 million point 3 or something and I'm asking what are those projects are they sewer and water projects or what projects are they they are sewer projects thank you there's a difference
between capital thank you was referencing was our operating budget capital projects are separate from our operating budget there's a capital budget and operating budget right these are capital costs in the store in this
away and that's where it's going to be spent thank you any additional comments
on resolution 25 hearing none mr. Harris mr. metta mr. Roy mr. Glees mr.
all right mr. Hirsch all right resolution number 26 2025 approving an amended capital project list to be funded by the proceeds of the city of Leicester general obligation bond series 2022 motion to approve second we have a
motion and a second that's all right thank you this resolution for 20 or excuse me this resolution is similar to resolution number 25 um except this is for uh this pertains to the 2022 water fund um the adjustments total 5.3 million dollars thank you very much council
royals so to reiterate funds in the water for use for capital projects in the water fund funds that were left over that were not used um not needed after projects were completed and being reallocated to other projects on the list for the water fund that is correct council president thank you very much any additional council comments on the resolution from the public just a quick question
um so when when were these projects due to be completed because we're looking at 2018 bonds in 2022 so what project in 2018 was completed and we have money left over but we didn't use that money toward the 2022 when we took out bonds in the 2018 bond issue that we just addressed then on the 2022 list so the 2018 bond project was not completed in 2022 it just now got completed is that my understanding there are some projects that do take that long yeah right but we're talking about these specific projects for
the money for resolution 26 we're talking about right projects in the water fund right that that
just got completed in now in 2024 and we found out that this money is left over yes projects do take several years right and now okay let me ask you a little bit differently right i don't think you're following me so in 2018 we had projects that were we took out bonds for the sewer and those projects got completed when that we now have this money left over they only got completed in 2025 right okay well this one's 2022 the one before was 2018 so the projects that got completed they just got completed in 2025 some of them yes some of these that were funded and you have a list of them which ones they were and how much was left because maybe that would make more sense to me yes because that's kind of like what I'm asking because we're borrowing more bond money and we're having bond money left and we're paying interest on this stuff you could send it to me you don't have to be if you will if you will you know that to me that will be fine I would like to see that and know what projects were completed and how much was left from each project
thank you thank you and I do think I don't see director Campbell either actually but there's your Tina Campbell I believe you had presented these with uh could you just speak very briefly if these are available uh online as well
someone who might know the answer the project lists are attached as exhibits to the resolutions
that are online okay all right so attached directly to the council agenda thank you okay appreciate that but still happy to send them might have them in my email once i can get to it i will have tabs open any additional comments from the public on resolution number 26.
hearing none mr harris mr mann aye mr roya aye mr cleese aye mr craig aye mr hirsch aye
and president bacon aye next item on the agenda resolution number 27 2025 mr harris a resolution
of the council of the city of lancaster authorizing the administration to execute a financial assistance application on behalf of the city to the pennsylvania infrastructure investment authority for replacement of lead water service lines motion to approve so we have a motion and a second
councillor uh thank you council president this resolution authorizes application for a penvest loan up to the amount of approximately 1.7 million dollars to go towards confirmation and replacement of known lead service lines this resolution authorizes submission of the application not necessarily to accept loan funding this administrative requirement from penvest city estimates uh this covered costs for approximately 108 water service lines with an estimated cost of 6 to 20 000 per line as many of you know our discussions here at council this is an unfunded mandate from the epa and thus the city is starting to prepare for the massive cost of the project the city is hoping to have these funds available to help defray this cost for property owners particularly since invest loans come with much lower interest rates as was stated than bond financing but are mostly limited to water sewer infrastructure projects like this also there's also grant funding that is available but has to be you basically have to apply as a loan to access that funding that was also stated by director campbell i'm just going to end my comment by saying each one of us can play a role in keeping these costs down for the city the city is still inventorying water service lines so you can do so in your basement go and take a picture of the water service line and send it to the city all those details are online and um by reporting that and reminding our neighbors to respond to that inventory that will reduce the cost of the inventory for the city and i just i will always take a moment to remind folks about that thank
Thank you very much, Councillor Hirsch. Just a question for you, because you mentioned it, and I want to put a fine point on it. The point of this funding application, this application for funding, is to complete lead line replacement at no cost to residents.
Correct. Thank you. And that could range depending on, my understanding is, it could range depending on what the nature of that, because there's the pot-bullying procedure, which a more expensive way of figuring out what the what the material is um and then there's you know from that to the full replacement that's that range of the six to twenty thousand costs that would be covered for the for these great thank you any additional council comments
on the resolution from the public you say there's going to be no call starting bird and street no cost to the residents but if it's a loan because right now you're applying for a loan it's not a grant so if we don't get a grant where there be other action by council to vote on if it's a loan because if it does become a loan that is going to be a cost to the residents no i'm not
denying that at all what i'm saying is that in this particular case what we're hoping to have these funds available for is actually assisting homeowners with the replacement of the lead water service line yeah so that's what i meant when i said no cost i didn't mean that there's no cost i mean obviously we're you know this is 1.7 million dollars in debt financing uh there's a cost with that it's it's what i was trying to say is that on an individual basis we're trying to make these funds available for homeowners because it is an unfunded mandate so any money that we can get in to help property owners that might not be able to handle you know a 20 000 water service land in placement that's why we're trying to get this money in right so but
it's gonna be a loan but the application itself is for a loan or for a grant the
application is for a loan and by doing that that opens up the opportunity for grant funding from Penvest is that correct Director Tina Campbell's nodding yes
right so I mean I just want to clarify that because if we're getting a loan there is going to be a cost to the taxpayer I was going to pay right and
okay yes our rate payers may see an impact if this is a loan on a grant
let me just this question so I don't have to get up again and so the purpose of applying for two separate applications that reason is because I know we have an application fee why can't we not combine them both for one application for Penn Vest? I think it's just because of the nature of these two
projects are totally different. Like one is related to the interior service line and then the other is for the water main that is going from Susquehanna to the treatment plant, from the treatment plant to the distribution network. So it's not a
guideline through Penn Vest that we can apply for one and get and only pay one application fee instead of applying for two separate applications and paying two
separate application fees okay that's what I was asking if there was a way we
could it would be nice but they don't allow it and if I recall correctly I
think that's the city is trying to do that because by focusing on specific neighborhoods where there's a high number of known service lines that need to be replaced, that those could be lumped together to exactly what you're saying, like reduce that amount of fees so we don't have to pay each time and plot. Right, and just for the public, how much is the
application fee for Penvest? Hi, thank you very much for the question. I honestly do
not know what the fee is it varies by application and by the magnitude of the cost and it's not necessarily the same percentage for every for every
application and just to clarify it's only for a hundred and eight service
lines in the city that was the estimate given by this it could possibly more or
last depending on how she yes and we we knew ten years ago that this was an issue it should have been done ten years ago it's sad that we had to wait this long and strain the taxpayers to crunch up these numbers and be responsible for this debt but I really need a copy of the hundred and eight service lines of homes that are going to be receiving this because a hundred and eight service lines is that just are you saying within the home or service lines throughout the city throughout the city and to be clear the city has been updating these led service lines this is I guess being expedited that process because of the deadline you're already past the deadline that's why because they
basically accelerated the timeline on this process mm-hmm and out of the interior lines as well I didn't know I don't know if you want to speak to that
Mr. Rauch just to say the city has been replacing lead laterals off the water lines for decades which is why we have so few the the new law that has been passed both accelerates the remaining replacement of those lead lines those laterals of which there are less than 1% out of the 50,000 lines that are across our water distribution service area what is new is that this utilities are now responsible for the line that is coming from the curb into the house that was only ever contemplated as being private property and under the Biden administration that law was changed and so the city has been doing work that it has been required to do to replace all of our laterals what is new is the replacement of what would have been previously understood as private property that is now our job that is now a burden that repairs will have to carry because there is not enough federal grant money to meet the demand across the country and this is a point of advocacy through the Water Council and the US Conference of Mayors and other groups that I'm affiliated with because they do understand the impact of our repairs but it has it but it was a
problem it's always been a problem and it's I'm sorry once it then when when is the deadline hearse no the deadline that you have we're already at the 10th year then no it's from now it starts any years from now yeah thank you miss
government thank you any additional comment from the public on resolution number 27 hearing none mr. Harris mr. man mr. Roy mr. please mr. Harris resolution number 28 2025 mr. Harris the resolution of the Council of the City of Lancaster
authorized the administration to execute financial assistance assistance application on behalf of the city to the Pennsylvania infrastructure investment authority for construction of the susquehanna large diameter transmission
mains the motion and a second councillor thank you council president this
resolution authorizes an application for a pen invest loan up to the amount of forty nine million two hundred ninety three thousand dollars to go towards the Susquehanna large diameter transmission mains both of phase two the finished water transmission main that's the one that goes from the water treatment plant to the oyster point reservoir and phase three which is going from the treatment plan, from the river to the treatment plan. Relating to phase two, that transmission mean is beyond its useful life on paper, so it's an urgent concern, a priority for the city to address its replacement. PEMBES requires projects to be shovel-ready before we can apply for financing for the project, so because this project is still working through permits design and that process takes years for products of this scale the city may pursue in our bank financing until the project can be fully funded by the penvest this will help the city avoid multi-year interruptions in the process of replacing this water main interim financing would mainly be for pieces of equipment materials needed to make sure that the project doesn't get stalled given how critical it is and also the fact that there's a deadline on a three million dollar grant to purchase equipment to start this project so he wants to ensure once construction begins on the project that doesn't stall at any point due to lack of financing or disruptions with supply chain etc thank
you very much councillor Hirsch any comments from council on resolution
number 28 Thank you, Council President. I just want, maybe just questions for Director Campbell. The interim financing as well as the PennVest loan, we've looked at the budgetary impact it would have, and it is aligned with our projections.
Yes. So we had included this, when we were looking at the 2025 bond last month, we included did this in the overall projections so it would have been part of the graphs
that you saw in those projections and clarify again how much did you say you're
looking for for this resolution 49 million and this is in addition to the
41 million bond that council approved just a couple Councils ago, is that correct?
Correct. This is for a different project, but yes
For a different project. I thought that was for the water main as well The large diameter water main. Yeah
From the graphs that we had when we did the bond Presentation, it had the pedestal in gold or in a different color and that was not a part of the original bond, but that budget tear impact was still projected out over the life of the bond.
We talked about it at that time.
So we're talking about maybe $90 million we will be borrowing and taxpayers will be footing that bill?
Rate payers in the water system?
Tax payers. Oh, rate payers will pay? The $90 million utility? Yes. Even for the PennVest loan? Correct. Okay, very good. Infrastructure is extremely expensive. I have learned this. It really is. And since we do have 10 years, and I did attend a water meeting that the Public Works Department put on, it was a very good meeting, very informative. I want to encourage members of the public when council or when the city does put on these meetings to attend because you do learn a lot. And I know that they are working on a plan for the future, a comprehensive plan that may extend our timelines possibly. So while we're saying we only have 10 years now, we did learn that that time could be extended. it so i think council really needs to consider before they vote about the cost that you're putting on and like you said the water companies the rate payers and we know that the city pays the highest rate right now and we know that's going to be looked into but you really need to consider that because government has set up where we can look at other ways of getting meeting the epa requirements and doing that at a lower cost to the rate payer and extending our time so that the 10 years could be extended depending on the comprehensive plan that the water did i understand that well right if i may uh thank you mr um just to clarify you're
talking about two different things i am so appreciative that you went to the combined sewer overflow meeting which i'm going to actually give in my talk about my mayor's report that is different than the 10-year timeline for the lead and copper rule so we're talking about three different things tonight we're talking about infrastructure replacement which is the 42-inch main which is what is being considered now we're talking about a lead line replacement which is an unfunded mandate that is separate that is another cost and then we're also in a few minutes i'm going to talk about the combined sewer overflows and the long-term control plan which is all three
of those things are different thank you additional comments from the public on resolution number 28
mayor i'm listening to what you're saying you're talking about three different things but we are also talking about um funding that was uh available from to that to 2018 to 2022 that is being moved over into administrative projects or other other you know projects that could be used for purposes such as the water main you can't use it
for that are you speaking about the what as far as the bonds yeah which you're gonna get her a copy of where that's going to we can't change the bond at the
allocations of those funds ministry but you could use it for some of that so
that the bond can decrease no that's not true you can't I think mr. Harris just mentioned that it's available on the website with the materials for the meeting. It lists the projects from 2018. That was for the sewer fund. Then there's the water fund. Those were projects from 2022. Those are projects that are listed in the attachment for the materials. What we are talking about are different projects than what is on either of those lists.
I understand that but projects with funding left over should be used by council for specific reasons to not burden the taxpayer so much you know I mean there's got to be other ways that you can use that we're not the experts we're the taxpayers we pay you the salary so that you can figure it out I mean just try to make it make sense if there's funding available here that can be used for anything else other than specific projects that she's going to submit documents to to miss bird about why not use it for these things so that you can't continue to burden the taxpayers i mean we're already seeing so much of a burden i understand and appreciate your question and i i
hear you but when we issue a bond when we take out indebtedness we must submit a project list and we can't change that midstream legally it's legal no no legally yeah so i hear you and appreciate what you're asking but we're not able to take the funds out of the bond and use it for something that we didn't say we're going to use it for in the first place but they're asking you
to consider the amount and i heard her say that to have to consider the numbers that's all i'm
asking to any additional comments in the public on resolution 28 here you know
mr. Harris
that is resolution number 29 2025 mr. Harris a resolution to make
declaration of official intent to reimburse short-term financing used for the susquehanna large diameter transmission mains project with funds received from the pennsylvania infrastructure investment authority motion to approve second we have a motion and a second
counselor thank you council president this resolution is really or resolution 29 is related to resolution 28 and that it pertains to the penvest funding that's being applied for that we were just talking about as stated the city may need to utilize short-term financing in the amount of 27 million to keep the susquehanna large diameter transmission mains projects moving and this resolution fulfills an administrative requirement from penvest to have a resolution stating that the official intent of the city is to pay down this short-term financing when the penvest funds are received so in other words stating our intent to refinance the short-term financing with more favorable lower interest and best funds when we receive that that's a requirement from penvest and this resolution meets that requirement thank you very much
counselor i think we had a conversation during committee um about the types of things that we could do in the interim and how we could keep the projects moving namely purchasing equipment and the impacts of waiting to purchase that equipment because of inflation and the tariffs and the unknown but known impact that it's going to the prices are going to go up so by doing this we get ensure the best rate on purchasing that equipment is that a correct characterization of director campbell's comments that's my understanding he's nodding in the back Thank you. Council comments on the resolution. From the public on resolution 29. Hearing none, Mr. Harris. Mr. Mitten. Aye. Mr. LaRocque. Aye. Mr. Cleese. Aye. Mr. Gregg. Aye. Mr. Hirsch. Aye. And President Bacon. Aye. Resolution number 30 is our next item. Mr. Harris.
A resolution of the Council of the City of Lancaster authorizing the filing of an application for funding through the Department of Conservation and Natural Resources community conservation partnership program in the amount of one million three hundred eighty five thousand and thirty five dollars to be used for South Hennant Park motion to approve second we have a
motion and a second council Herschel thank you council president this resolution authorizes the city of Lancaster to apply for 1.385 million dollars in grant funds from dcnr's community conservation partnership program to go towards improvements at south end park these funds would go toward upgraded play equipment a multi-purpose field basketball court upgrades improved ada access water play new fencing and improved seating and lighting at south end park it's granted the city's estimating would cover 50 of that cost and there are other grant funding sources the city's waiting to hear back on such as the local shares account that could go towards this project thank you very much any
council comments on a resolution 30 from the public hearing on mr. Harris next item is resolution number 31 2025 mr. Harris
and Natural Resources Community Conservation Partnership Program in the amount of seventy four thousand nine hundred and sixty dollars to be used for
Reservoir Park. Motion to approve. Second. We have a motion and a second. Councilor Hirsch. Thank you Council President. This resolution authorizes City of Lancaster to apply for seventy four thousand nine hundred sixty dollars in grant funds from the Community conservation partnership program as mentioned to go towards preparing a master plan for Reservoir Park improving Reservoir Park was identified as a high priority in the city's parks master plan and as referred to in this resolution Reservoir Park has a lot of potential and a lot of potential uses and so for these reasons the city would like to prepare a master plan for Reservoir Park
thank you very much Councillor Hirsch additional comments from Council on
resolution 31 from the public Darlene Byrd I heard you say on the other one for South End Park that you were looking for a match from other grants does this require a match Director Tina Campbell is nodding yes and where do we plan on getting that match for this I do not know okay so we're gonna approve council is going to approve that we apply for a grant and we don't know where the money's coming from to match it yet is that correct I'm hearing for this
resolution 31 it's coming from the 2025 bond funds that were just approved thank
you so we already borrowed the money for the match for this project through the
bond we have reached the end of our legislative agenda this evening which
will move us into our second public comment period it's open for comments on issues that were not on the agenda again duration of comments is limited to three minutes per speaker please begin with your name and your residence your block
of residence for our public records good evening my name is Taylor Enterline Mannheim Borough but I my name is Taylor Enterline I'm reading this statement on behalf of John Minda the founder of the Black Voter Outreach Network of Pennsylvania Mayor Sirachi I am addressing you directly this evening because your administration is overseeing a regression in public trans transparency that is deeply troubling and quite frankly unacceptable just last quarter in quarter four of 2024 the lancaster city police department published a use of force report that included data disagreed by race and age that report told an important story 36 of use of force cases involved the latino residents 20 involved black residents and seven incidences involved minors children that level of detail helped the community understand who is most impacted by use of force and provided a foundation for meaningful oversight now mayor those details are gone the recently updated dashboard on the police department's website is cleaner but that is where progress stops it strips away the most essential data points there is no racial or ethnic breakdown no information on minors in no access to previous quarterly reports the graph presented on the page is visually misleading and hard to interpret no explanation was provided no public update was issued and the change was not even disclosed during the April 1st Public Safety Committee meeting where chief Mendez spoke at length to make matters worse the number of reported use to force incidents for quarter 4 2024 has quietly dropped from 39 incidences previously documented to 29 now shown on the dashboard that's a 25% decrease with no explanation what changed are these incidences being reclassified are we using a new metric are some incidents no longer being counted if we can't answer those questions then the public can't trust the data we are calling this what it is a rollback of transparency in the middle of a community crisis around policing it is one thing to issue talking points about accountability but it is another thing entirely to quietly remove the very information that allows for accountability to exist when you withhold data you withhold the truth and that decision breaks the fragile trust between City Hall and the communities who are asking to be seen heard and protected mayor sirachi you have said that the police oversight boards have no power there are cities across this country including here in Pennsylvania that have passed civilian review boards with investigative authority and subpoena power Lancaster can do the same the real question is whether the political will exists in closing I respectfully submit the following questions to you and ask that you respond in writing to the public before the next council meeting one who made the decision to remove the demographic and age-related data from the police use of force reports to why were City Council members in the public not informed about this change three will your administration commit to restoring the full disaggregated reports including past quarters for public view public review for if not please I gotcha if not please explain why this data is no longer appropriate or relevant for public access and five do you believe the data transparency is essential for public accountability thank you for your time and we expect honest answers in real action thank you Brian Nelson
Africa Canyon Circle Drive so I understand while public safety remains a concern the handling of children should not result in an incident of police misconduct or excessive force and it shouldn't be up to the department to decide if it was excessive force that's up to us in the community. It is my belief that community engagement should be done through the office of the mayor or city council, not the department. That consolidates power with them, not us. So I have a pop quiz for you guys. The Citizen Police Review Board is an independent agency within blank created in 1997 to investigate citizen complaints about improper conduct by the blank Bureau of Police through a referendum. I'll let you know that that city is the city of Pittsburgh in pennsylvania and perhaps it is time that we demand a referendum ourselves it's not in the cba but it didn't matter to the people of pittsburgh and better yet they offered their citizens to join those meetings by zoom citizen advisory boards exist and they have been done some with genuine authority pittsburgh is an example now it can't be done with no authority as in philadelphia but they have been done i think that this is something you guys really need to look into because it sounds like you saying that this is something that's not possible just sounds like an excuse to not do it or not put in the effort to work with us we've already seen that the lancaster city police isn't willing to come to the table i have zero faith in their community engagement office if it's not done through citizens there's nothing we can do to do anything better in our community if you guys aren't bringing us to the table we've heard from a number of groups today that can contribute to community policing as well some of them have left and the people who came to speak in favor of the police are now suddenly gone however i just want to let you know that since 1994 the u.s department of justice has provided grants to over 13 000 law enforcement agencies to support community policing initiatives highlighting the importance that it has in our justice system these are things that you guys can do we've just told you what it is i expect you the guys to actually make an effort to look into it
thank you good evening my name is Duncan Hopkins I live in the northeast part of the city and I want to start out with a question addressing some of the comments earlier in this earlier in this meeting as well as last week why are we spending our time characterizing these kids who were assaulted by police officers as violent they were riding their bikes without lights which is a civil offense and not a criminal one. Yet in the chief's presentation last week and in some comments from folks here tonight, we've been treating these kids like criminals. Traffic safety is important. Ten years ago, I was biking to work when I was hit by a car just half a block from here and I was very lucky not to be seriously injured. I also was riding with bike lights on and it was daylight. I've had plenty of close calls, so I certainly understand the need for safety. Every single person in this room does, but that's not what we need to focus on tonight. What we need to focus on tonight is that when the police enforce the laws on the books, they need to do so in an appropriate manner. What took place on March 2nd was a clear as day example of police brutality. I dare anyone to watch that video in full, listening to the screams of those kids who are afraid they might join the long list of minors who were murdered by a cop that encounter was unacceptable and the consequences for riding bikes without lights should not be being pinned to the ground by an officer with a history of misconduct I'm speaking about officer Hatfield last week chief Mendez stood up here to give a presentation on police use of force and while I have many thoughts two main things stood out to me first the chief spent a long time talking about how use of force reports are reviewed within the department and no time at all on whether and how discipline would be passed on to the offending officer I think he said and discipline may be applied if if it's acceptable that was it it is unacceptable that he declined to speak about officer discipline in his report second every single council member had the opportunity to ask the chief questions some councillors used that opportunity to ask about increased transparency, oversight, and a different use of force policy for minors. However, other councillors declined to use this rare opportunity to ask questions in a public forum. For councillors to give up the opportunity to ask Chief Mendes the tough questions that the community has been asking for a month is frankly insulting. And lastly, I'm tired of the back and forth, I'm tired of the excuses, and I wish that this body would spend its time trying to find solutions instead of just waiting for the storm to blow over you all have difficult jobs and i get that but you signed up for it and you signed up to represent your community we have a real opportunity to change our city for the better and it is disheartening to see my city government prioritizing quiet over justice chief mendez has said multiple times that the community has needs to come to the table we're here it's time for this council mayor sirachi and chief mendez to listen thank you very much sunny
D'Astra, 700 block of New Holland Avenue. Act three, a vision for public involvement. If acts one and two were about access and process, this final part is about voice, about creating spaces where the community can engage with institutions that serve them. Yesterday I introduced online a draft ordinance to establish a community police review board. This board would function in an advisory capacity without disciplinary authority, focusing on reviewing policies, procedures, and patterns to provide recommendations aimed at that enhancing public safety and trust. This model isn't unprecedented. In Philadelphia, the Citizens Police Oversight Commission operates similarly and has subpoena power, offering recommendations that led to policy changes within the police department. While it didn't have disciplinary power, its influence contributed to reforms. The goal here is not to undermine law enforcement, but to build a bridge between the police and the community through transparency and dialogue by identifying areas for improvement and suggesting policy enhancements such a board can play a vital role in fostering mutual respect and understanding with council members up for election and others seeking higher office the direction we choose now will shape the future of public safety in our city this draft ordinance is a starting point open for discussion and refinement i've pushed the boulder you decide whether it is up a hill or down the hill the essential question is whether we are committed to creating avenues for meaningful community participation and shaping the policies that impact us all anyway that's all for tonight folks thanks for tuning into the Tony show see
you next time good evening Diane Desmond again off route 30 by the state police we've heard some positives tonight about the police department by members of the public but I'd like to be clear that whatever positives may exist do not erase the concerns that the community has voiced and the shortcomings of the police department. I do find it interesting and frankly disturbing that most members of the public who felt frightened by these youth and advocated for harsh punishment were white. As a white person addressing members of council and members of the community, many of whom are white, I urge you to sit with the discomfort of my observation here tonight. Use that discomfort to reflect and appreciate how frightened these youth feel when facing use of force from an armed officer. Are these feelings of fear comparable? We are still deeply concerned about the policing of youth and the disproportionate use of force against black and brown youth, which I would like to clarify and acknowledge is a nationwide issue that Lancaster is not separate from. we receive verbal confirmation that the proposal from Baltimore on the policing of youth will be reviewed considered and an update on your decision will be given to the public verbally during an upcoming City Council meeting and I would also like to further know by which date thank you
evening Brianna Sienkiewicz block of 700 block of Marietta this is my take on april 1st the lancaster community showed up yet again to city hall to demand the end of police brutality this time we heard police chief mendez give off and give an off-topic report that blatantly ignored our demands and attempted to shift blame for his department's egregious use of force against teen bike riders on march 2nd on to the community his presentation was filled with irrelevant stats and policies which addressed none of the tangible concerns and actual demands yes i don't think that chief mendez presentation was random he went on and on about gun seizure data emphasized on teens and early 20s sending a clear message that the police still are operating under the assumption that black and brown bodies are guilty until proven innocent and armed until proven otherwise this is a thinly veiled attempt to blame victims and alienate um and alleviate any police accountability chief mendez stated during the community outcry that public safety is a two-way street mendez is correct but neglects the two key points the community showed up and offered actionable demands that were laid out and continue to be laid out building trust takes time patience and a willingness to be wrong none of which were demonstrated by chief mendez nor the mayor during this committee meeting during doing trust it means opening up the floor to residents split directly to those who have power including chief mendez we were not given in that opportunity and so I don't believe him when he says public safety is a two-way street and involves all of us in addition to denying the rights of citizens to speak truth to power he failed to acknowledge the community's pain for decades of injustice and mistrust from racist policies and policing this pain cannot be erased by patting yourselves on the back for a few years of doing better the onus of chain falls on the shoulders of those in powers if residents are not engaged with police events the answer is not to take personal demands um personally and demand the residents show up it's to open up a safe form to ask why and what can be done police brutality should never happen but it does and the answer is not to shift blame but or listing harmful statistics of justification of use of force but to ask why why couldn't trained officers handle these citations such as the incident on march 2nd and what can be done to prevent future situations of police brutality from occurring Abram X. Kendi states, pain is usually essential to healing. When it comes to healing America of racism, we want to heal America without pain, but without pain, there is no progress. At the end, it was clear Police Mendez and the mayor said members and some members of city council were unwilling to wade into that pain and join us on a two-way street to healing and policy reform. without addressing our pain or demands we will continue to be two ships passing in the night instead of meeting on an equal playing field out beyond right-doing and wrongdoing until open this open discussion and honest cooperation can be had we the community are left to wrestle with knowing we have a long fight ahead of us thank you thank you good evening good evening my name is
Betty Jones, South End, 200 block of South End Street, I should say. Okay, I'm here again to talk about the trash situation that occurred about a month or so ago back. From the whole block, the whole southeast section, 100 block, 200, all the way down to the 400 block, We received citations, I would call it, for trash, which I came here before and I spoke about it. And I even showed pictures. When I received the citation, I called. And the person I spoke with, she told me that someone had called and complained about it. okay I I took pictures and if you can see yourself it was it was windy so trash was blowing all over the place anytime trash can come from 100 block all the way down to the 400 block I know everyone did not all of a sudden just put trash out I did not move trash so I'm coming here again to counselors to ask for your help that's why I came because I don't usually come out and do things like this but this is important to me and they they told us we have to pay $225 plus the $200 fee now so that's $225 that is due for each tenant or I should say owner in the 200 in the southeast area so I just want to know what cops gonna do about this and you know to help us I've seen us it's not just me but our whole section you know a whole block from the 100 all the way down to the 400 block you guys are here I'm coming to you because you supposed to be here to fight for us so this is what I'm coming for some kind of
results thank you yeah it's shameful to be up here at this podium when we didn't select this job, we ask that you represent the people for this position. It's shameful that we have to be looked at on a psychological standpoint, because you're used to psychologically digesting a patient. And things are just being overlooked, such as Betty's trash issue. You don't have an answer for her?
I've been communicating with Ms. Berg and Director Campbell,
Okay, well it's my time, so I wish Art Morris was here so I can just clearly state that has anyone ever seen the one-wheel bikers that are cross, go throughout our streets, that basically interfere with traffic, they run in and out of cars, I know you all seen them, it's one-wheel bike and there's a bunch of them, and they go all over the street. they do not follow the rules so for Art Morris to stand here and talk about our children not using specific things that maybe neighborhood engagement could have been targeting to help teach our kids about bike safety because of neighborhood engagement there are so many different types of resources that we you know that we have that we're not getting from you guys such as a simple question about a trash issue she shouldn't have to come here you don't think she's old enough she should be home resting and you too you know the city has become this is not a metropolitan area you are forcing this city to be a metropolitan area therefore we're this square block radius that we have is being disrupted on all sides and all levels our kids they are used to going into the streets. We have bikers. We have one-wheel bikers going all over the streets. I don't understand it. I just don't understand. And then lastly, Harrisburg adopted a bill, Mayor Sirachi. They adopted the bill that was given to you guys and it's in the mayor's hands. This bill can be passed. It's up to Mayor Sirachi. The burden stands on you. You can make changes in this city. You just choose not to. Karen Schultz from the boys and girls club has she sits in her her desk and she looks out the window and sees these things happening but is she sending out brochures is she sending out invitations or do the boys and girls club have any meetings about bike safety she's been sitting there for two years yeah I haven't had a flyer yet I'm pretty sure if I go around the block with benchmark with the other gentleman that introduced this new v1 prevention program he probably doesn't even live in the city not only does he not live in the city he probably hasn't even had a chance to walk four blocks down the road to even speak to them people about his prevention plan but he got him he got a grant for it right yeah I understand that but have some respect for us stop looking at us with this scare tactic and a psychological review thing and we're tired of it answer questions get things done thank you blacks and brown kids should not have to go through this this is too
much this is too much
Lopez Lancaster City I do have I kind of want to have a little exchange real confusion bear with me um what is like when you guys come in you take office um you like have like an ethics oath right like what you hear in your chambers which you deal with on the day-to-day in these council meetings like how you handle certain things and i wish janet diaz was here for what i'm about to say because i'm very very disgusted that every time she leaves these chambers she jumps on her phone and starts to attack people but doesn't say anything from these seats and it bothers me last week like my my emails like what she said about me and text messages aside I really don't care grown but last week she went online after she left council chambers and made a statement about counselor in my head that provoked racist comments about his religious practices and it was a direct attack that was so unnecessary like I really really need to know what is supposed to be becoming of our council members and what disciplinary matters happen when things like this transpire because why does she keep being allowed to do things like this to people and sit in that seat and get paid by the members of this community but do they go online and publicly attack people's race where they're from and what their religion is are they sending text messages at 12 12 in the morning asking why constituents are coming up here and demanding results at this point why do we keep allowing her to finish out her little term here it's distasteful to the community It should be disrespectful to each and every one of you at this point. And what gets done? Was there even a conversation had with her after the last situation that transpired on social media? Because I have the screenshots.
May I respond to that, Ms. Lopez? Thank you. First of all, I agree that the comment was racist and disgusting. Second, I couldn't see it because she has me blocked.
She has me blocked, too, so I sent it to me.
And to your question about what disciplinary action is possible, she reports to all of you. She doesn't report to me, she doesn't report to the mayor, she reports to the voters.
So what can, I mean, outside of her already being about to be on her way out because she's dang sure ain't about to be our mayor, what can we do intermittently to get her out of that chair
chair because she don't belong there i would like to have a longer conversation about this but diana's just speaking generalities that i know it's very difficult to remove a municipal government member in the state of pennsylvania it's a state matter but um yes that's my short version of that answer and that but i do hear what you're saying no and i appreciate that and i'm not going to
say much more but that speaks to the people watching on live to really really pay attention of who we're putting in these seats that we can't remove once they get there thank you
was a good statement as we have these council members sitting here and we continue to come whether it's a police issue a trash issue what are we going to do i mean i'm here to challenge council um we've sat here for eight years and i've come to council and i've spoken i've spoken with with the mayor, we do not have a plan for the southeast area. When is council going to go to the economic development and say, we need a plan for the southeast of Lancaster? We talk about housing. We talk about policing. We talk about the trash issues. We talk about parks. And we're doing all these comprehensive plans. But yet, we do not have a plan for the southeast of Lancaster. And then when we come here and we talk about black and brown children, and we say, well, we don't have a plan. city don't even have a plan for the area which is mostly highly populated i mean it speaks volumes and it's time that council at least requires that the department of economic and community development you hire consultants for every area in the city and we paid consultants to come up with plans and yet we have not a plan for the southeast area i'm asking council to respond to that now Not wait till the next election to see if you sit in the seat again, but do something now. I'm also here talking about a stop sign. We asked for a stop sign in 2019. I continue to come up here and we talk about safety and safe neighborhoods. And we're told repeatedly why we can't do anything to prevent accidents. Well, there wasn't enough accidents on that corner reported. So what? There was enough near misses. And everywhere else you can look at preventive measures, But when it comes to addressing issues in the Southeast, we don't look at preventive measures. A stop sign on South End and Green Street is a preventive measure. We're tired of asking. We're tired of keep coming and coming and coming. And I agree. I vote for people that I hope is going to represent me. I don't want to show up at council every meeting. If that was the case, I would run for city council. I'm not running because I believe I'm electing people that's going to vote and speak in my best interest and the interest of the residents, especially in the South and Concern neighborhood. So I'm asking you to do something about not having a plan in the Southeast area now, not next year, not three years from now. Start developing a plan for the Southeast. Thank you.
Any additional comments from this period? Ms. Desmond, I'll just remind you that you did speak already in this period, so I'll let you go very, very briefly.
It is a very brief question, and I appreciate that. Thank you so much. Last week, I did have a question about the water rates and how we're going to be impacted as residents the percentage that we might anticipate of the water rates going up as a result of the improvement projects I found myself so relieved that it wasn't going to affect me potentially so I did not receive an answer to that question and I just sort of skipped off to my seat and that was a disservice to the community in Lancaster so I would just like to see if there is an answer that the community can receive and by which date they would receive that anticipated increase in their rates.
Thank you. Thank you. Director Campbell, follow up with you about timeline for rate cases because those rates are determined by those PUC rate cases, which as we spoke at last meeting have a timeline of anywhere between eight plus months, so thank you. Any additional comments for this period? Hearing none, we'll close public comment this evening and we'll move to the report of the mayor mayor siraji uh thank you
council president um related to the use of force data i i want to acknowledge that we have made changes to use the force data by adding historical data not just the most recent quarter i also want to acknowledge that that there is not currently data related to race and ethnicity or age but that that will be added by the end of the week and we should have acknowledged that in a note on the website as we are making these changes to um address some of the questions that have been raised um i want to also just indicate and i um i believe that i can i can give this information uh to you but the data that we are reporting um uh has changed uh due to our accreditation and the ways in which we are counting use of force has changed so that after 4-1-25 there will be additional data that is being collected so calls for service with no arrests after 4-1 would be included in the use of force data arrests not requiring force would be included in the use of force data arrests requiring force were always included in the use of force data so all this to say that the data is going to look different after after 4-1 because of the accreditation process and so we will note this more clearly on the website it should clarify the change in the collection how the reporting data which will be more and and and include again the race and ethnicity and age so that data is um is going to be available by the end of the week so i just wanted to let council know that the second thing is that the department of public works recently held a public meeting on the city's long-term control plan which mr was in attendance uh to reduce uh combined sewer overflows into the conestoga river as i mentioned we are um four major issues that we are trying to address presently um and i have spoken about this in my state of the city as a perfect storm of um both unfunded mandates uh as well as the need for improvements in our infrastructure and as council president pointed out it's all very expensive so in addition to the combined sewer system and the long-term control plan we have the lead and copper line regulations which have extended the responsibility of the city and the costs to rate payers as well as our aging infrastructure replacement needs as well as a pfos when you add all these things up it is a lot of money i do want to want to just focus my comments tonight on the combined sewer overflows and the long-term control plan so the city has made progress reducing our cso through the implementation of green infrastructure and other facility improvements and there's a lot more work to be done at the meeting uh christine volpe hilditch deputy director of public works for utility shared the city's work to comply with the u.s epa consent decree which was signed in 2017 and the development of our long-term control plan to minimize the impact of csos over time a few takeaways for council's awareness the city continues to evaluate multiple strategies to reduce combined sewer overflows including gray infrastructure upgrades green infrastructure temporary water storage and a separation of storm water from the sewer system the estimated cost to meet the cso regulations ranges from 30 million to 73 million dollars the implementation timeline will depend on the financial impact of residents meaning how quickly we proceed depends on what our community can afford this is a point of major contention because the federal government will take into consideration affordability only as it relates to our combined sewer overflows but not in relation to other mandates the city is continuing to assess cso reduction options gathering public input and identifying a preferred alternative that balances regulatory requirements with the economic environmental and community considerations unique to langster the next step is submitting our long term control plan to the epa initiating a process to finalize the cost timelines and methods for reducing cso's while there were very few people in attendance at the meeting this is really important that the community understand what is at sea there is a recording on the city's youtube channel and more information can be found at engage lancaster and i encourage council members to review the slides because as ms burke indicated that i do believe that was a very informative overview of both the challenges before us the work that has been done the progress that has been made and what it's what the work is now to submit the long-term control plan to a new administration which continues to evolve uh even as we speak thank you thank you very much mayor sirachi
next item is the report of president council i do have a brief report to give this evening i reflected a lot over the last month about the job and duty that we entrust our police officers with in leicester i've listened to city residents speak about interactions with police some positive some negative i respect and appreciate that it's a job that often brings you into situations with people who could be having the worst day of their lives i've also reflected a lot recently about the work that our police department has done over the last several years to respond to the needs of the community some of that response and work we heard about earlier this evening from organizations in our community we will also soon hear about the work the department has done to receive accreditation i do trust the internal controls and review processes of our department and believe that our officers are working in good faith with our community and i believe that continuous improvement and responsiveness is not only possible but necessary i trust that our police department will continue to uphold the high standards our community expects and deserves and i look forward to reviewing the information that was given to us this evening about different use of force options for you that concludes my comments council comments this evening
this is a common more question when these weather related trash concerns come up is there a way that the city could waive the fees or is there a way that the citizens can appeal the citations thank
you councilman yes there is an appeal process for citations and it is outlined there's certain number of days I don't have in front of me but they do need to I believe that they need to pay in the interim but I know for sure that they need to have the the the reason for the citation needs to be cleared in a certain number of days to avoid the additional penalty for having
it up. I'll follow up with Council President and Director Campbell and the Mayor with some additional questions. Thank you. Additional Council comments this evening. Council President. Council Craig. Thank you. The concerns that have arisen regarding recent reports of police using excessive force toward teenagers riding bikes downtown on our downtown streets. These concerns weigh heavily on me as I am a mother of six, five boys, 12 grandkids, sons and one great grandson. These concerns play heavily on me, as they should all of who are committed to ensuring the safety of every individual within our city, particularly our young people. First and foremost, I want to acknowledge the voices of those who have spoken out. Your concerns are valid and are a vital part of keeping our city government transparent and fair. As a member of City Council, my responsibility is to listen to you, understand your concerns, and work tirelessly to address them. This moment calls for us to reflect on the kind of community we want to build. One where young people can navigate through our neighborhoods without fear, where families can feel assured of their children's safety, and where law enforcement earns the trust of those they are sworn to protect. In doing so, I must recognize the public safety is a partnership between residents and police. Mutual respect and understanding are essential in fostering a community where everyone feels safe and valid. We must ensure that our local law enforcement embodies the values of fairness and respect, especially when interacting with our youth. To that end, I i reviewed the video footage and reports and i reviewed and i also reviewed the bicycle safety ordinance number 158 of 2023. in addition i also listened to community members thoughts and feelings regarding this incident to uncover what happened and why after this thorough review i have concluded that the youth were in violation of the bike riding safety protocol and when stopped did not cooperate with the police therefore the police acted within law enforcement practices and training protocols in stopping and detaining you as we move forward this moment calls for us to reflect on the kind of community we want to build one where young people can navigate their neighborhoods without fear where families can feel assured of their children's safety and where law enforcement earns the trust of those they are sworn to protect as a member of city council i'm committed to the safety of our young people and mutual respect and understanding of to foster a community where everyone feels safe and valued let us work together as partners and continue to build a city defined by fairness and mutual respect thank you for your engagement your vigilance and your commitment to our community well-being pretty much what i have to say you know i'm concerned about um all the things that have happened over the last few weeks that have centered around the incident that happened downtown um that could have been done very well one of my children one of my grandchildren and you know i have to do is try to try i have to try and do better you know it has to we have to meet at some happy medium and i really think that most of the things that have happened here some of it has been very brutal and you know the name calling unnecessary we're not going to get anything solved with calling each other name or thinking bad thoughts about each other we're going to have to sit down at the table discuss what needs to happen start making too many demands on each other thank you thank you
counselor any additional council comments this evening hearing none and having reached the end of our agenda i'll hear a motion to adjourn motion and a second all in favor we are adjourned thank
Thank you.